Luke 6
But I say to you
who hear, love your enemies.
Do good to those who
hate you. Bless those
who curse you. Pray for those who
abuse you. To one who strikes
you on the cheek, offer the other also.
And from one who takes away
your cloak, do not withhold your tunic
either. Give
to everyone who begs from you.
And from one who takes away your goods,
do not demand them back.
And as you wish that others would do to
you, do so to
them. If you
love those who love you, what
benefit is that to you? For even
sinners love those who love them.
And if you do good to those who do
good to you, what benefit is that
to you? For even sinners
do the same. And
if you lend to those from whom you expect
to receive, what credit is that
to you? Even sinners
lend to sinners to get back the same
amount. But love
your enemies, and do good
and lend, expecting nothing
in return. And your reward
will be great, and you will be
sons of the Most High.
For He is kind to the ungrateful
and the evil.
Be merciful, even
as your Father is merciful.
Judge not, and you will not be judged.
Condemn not, and you will
not be condemned. Forgive,
and you will be forgiven.
Give, and it will be given to
you. Good measure, pressed
down, shaken together, running over
will be put into your lap.
For with the measure you use,
it will be measured back to you.
He also told them
a parable. Can a blind
man lead a blind man?
Will they not both fall into a pit?
A disciple is not above his
teacher, but everyone when he is
fully trained will be like his
teacher. Why
do you see the speck that is in your brother's
eye, but do not notice the log
that is in your own eye?
How can you say to your brother,
Brother, let me take out
the speck that is in your eye, when you
yourself do not see the log that is in
your own eye? You hypocrite!
First,
take the log out of your own eye,
and then you will see clearly
to take out the speck that is in your
brother's eye.
For no good tree bears bad fruit,
nor again does a bad tree bear good
fruit. For each tree is known
by its own fruit.
For figs are not gathered from thorn bushes,
nor are grapes picked from
a bramble bush.
The good person out of the good treasure
of his heart produces good,
and the evil person out of his
evil treasure produces evil.
For out of the abundance
of the heart his mouth speaks.
Why
do you call me, Lord, Lord,
and not do what I tell you?
Everyone who comes to me and
hears my words and does them,
I will show you what he is like.
He is like a man building
a house, who dug deep
and laid the foundation on the rock,
and when a flood arose, the stream
broke against that house and could not
shake it, because it had been well
built. But the one who
hears and does not do them
is like a man who built a house on
the ground without a foundation.
When the stream broke against it, immediately
it fell, and the ruin of
that house was great.